ACTWU President Jack Sheinkman Additional Books, Memorabilia, and Files 5619 C-S MB
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU President Jack Sheinkman Additional Books, Memorabilia, and Files
1988-1997
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union (ACTWU)
Sheinkman, Jacob
5619 C-S MB
4.69 cubic feet
4.7 linear ft.
Records (documents), memorabilia.
Badges, campaign buttons, union buttons, certificates, plaques, awards, posters, tie tacks and pins
5674946
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 16, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 21, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5619 AV: ACTWU Audio-Visual Materials 5619 F: ACTWU Motion Picture Films 5619 G: ACTWU Graphics 5619 MB: ACTWU Memorabilia Collection 5619 mf: ACWA Records Parts 1-3 on Microfilm 5619 OH: ACWA Oral History Project Records 5619 P: ACTWU Photographs 5619 PUBS: ACTWU Publications 5619/001: ACTWU Collective Bargaining Agreements 5619/002: ACWA Education Department Records 5619/003: ACWA Sidney Hillman Scrapbooks 5619/004: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Files 5619/004 fiche: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Speeches on Microfiche 5619/005: ACWA Bessie Hillman Papers 5619/006: ACTWU Executive Vice-President's Office Files 5619/007: ACTWU Organizing Department Files 5619/008: ACWA Rieve-Pollock Foundation Files 5619/009: ACTWU Operations Department Sidney Hillman Awards Files 5619/010: ACWA Jacob Potofsky files 5619/011: ACTWU Southern Regional Joint Board Files 5619/012: ACTWU Company Files 5619/013: ACTWU Research Department Correspondence Chronological Files 5619/014: ACWA Local 169 Files 5619/015: ACTWU Department of Occupational Safety and Health Files 5619/015: ACTWU Department of Occupational Safety and Health Files
Collective bargaining--Textile industry.; Clinton, Bill, 1946-; Cuomo, Mario M., 1932-2015.; Gorbachev, Mikhail Sergeevich, 1931-; Gore, Albert, 1948-; Kirkland, Lane.; Koenig, Arthur.; Sallen, Charles.; Sargent, Ben.; Sheinkman, Jack.; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union.; AFL-CIO.; AFL-CIO. Industrial Union Department; AFL-CIO. Executive Council.; American Income Life Insurance Company.; American ORT Federation.; Americans for Democratic Action.; Coalition of Labor Union Women (U.S.); Hispanic Labor Committee.; International Chemical Workers Union.; International Textile, Garment and Leather Workers' Federation.; J.P. Stevens & Co.; Judea Mental Health Center.; National Cooperative Business Association (U.S.); National Rainbow Coalition (U.S.); New York Democratic Socialists of America.; United Federation of Teachers.; United Garment Workers of America.; United States Holocaust Memorial Museum.; United States. Martin Luther King, Jr., Federal Holiday Commission.; Workers' Defense League.; Workmen's Circle (U.S.). Home for the Aged of New York State (Bronx, New York, N.Y.); Zensen Domei (Japan); International Textile, Garment and Leather Workers' Federation.
5674946
- AFL-CIO Badges; Clinton campaign buttons (Box 1, Folder 1)
- ACTWU Buttons and misc. buttons (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  15 pieces
- Misc. buttons, ACTWU, National Rainbow Coalition, NYS AFL-CIO, CLUW, etc. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- ACTWU badge, misc. badge, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- International Textile, Garment, and Leather Workers' Federation Service Plaque (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Jack Sheinkman, President ACTWU, 1953-1995, A Visionary Leader Who Has Dedicated 42 Years to the Advancement of the Union Movement (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Plaque - Presented to Jack Sheinkman in Grateful Appreciation for your Dedicated ServiceLabor Committee, Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Commission, January 13, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- American ORT Federation Scholarship Award Presented to Amalgamated Clothing & Textile Workers Union Jack Sheinkman, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Plaque - Jack Sheinkman Charter Member, ACTWU Leadership Circle, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Plaque - The Department of the Treasury is Pleased to Present This Award to Jack Sheinkman, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- United States Holocaust Memorial Museum - Washington, D.C. - With Grateful Appreciation for Your Support presented to ACTWU (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Workmen's Circle Home & Geriatric Center 1st Annual Golf Tournament honors Jack SheinkmanMan of the Year, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- La Junta Directiva Del S.U.T.O.E.A. y los Trabajadores Textiles del Edo.Aragua Al Companero Jack SheinkmanMaracay-Venezuela, 03 Abril 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Jack Sheinkman Has been appointed as a Distinguished Member of the American Income Life Labor Advisory BoardMarch 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- The New York Region and The Center for Cultural Jewish Life of The Workmens Circle/Arbeter Ring Cordially Invites you to our 62nd Gala, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Certificate of Appreciation Presented to National Secretary-Treasurer Jack Sheinkman - 3/10/1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- International Chemical Workers Union, Jack Sheinkman, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- NCBA - Honored Cooperator, Lifetime Member Jack Sheinkman, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Pride, with deep appreciation to Jack Sheinkman for your effortsPride of Judea Mental Health Center, June 24, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Jesse L. Jackson and the National Rainbow Coalition presents the Clark-Waterhouse-King memorial Rainbow-Labor Award, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- The Hispanic Labor Committee, an Advisory Committee to the New York City Central Labor Council, AFL-CIO, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Special Thanks to Jack SheinkmanACTWU Local 2398, Johnsonville, SC, April 30, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Presented to ACTWU President, Jack SheinkmanLocal 2524 & Local 2526 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Cartoon by Ben Sargent (topic: J.P. Stevens & Co. Textile Mill, Collective Bargaining), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- ACTWU Logos (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Proclamation from Gov. Mario Cuomo about United Nations Day, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Certificate from MLK Fed Holiday Commission, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Plaque from Zensen, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Certificate from Mayor of San Antonio, TX, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Certificate - Bd. Of Trustees of Amalgamated Washable Clothing, Sportswear and Allied Industries Fund, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Letters from Pres. Clinton, Mario Cuomo; Certificates - Apartheid and Coal Strike, 1989-1996 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Proclamation of Labor History Month - Pres. Clinton, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Certificate - Italian Honors - "Il Presidente Della Repubblica", 1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Collage of Autographs - Joint Conf. of Textile and Apparel Worker's Unions - Japan/USA (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Eugene V. Debs/Norman Thomas Ward - Presented to Jack Sheinkman, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- The David L. Clendenin Award - This Plaque of Honor awarded to Jacob Sheinkman, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- The Labor Medal Presented to Jack Sheinkman {State of Israel Bonds], 1997 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- ACWTU wall mural poster, pen commemorating bill 6880-B from Mario Cuomo (from 12) (Box 5)
  - Awards, pen, small poster, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    "Social Democrats, U.S.A. on the occasion of its 1978 National Convention, is proud to pay tribute to Jacob Sheinkman, September 8, 1978"; "Portland, Maine ACTWU Wall Mural, "Together, We Will build the Future""; "State of New York, Executive Chamber,
- The Martin Luther King, Jr. Center for Nonviolent Social Change, Inc.: The King Center Labor Social Responsibility Award, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Presented to Jack Sheinkman, President, Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, AFL-CIO
- La Federacion de Trabajadores de la Industria Textil, Confeccion y sus Similares de Venezuela, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Otorgan el presente Reconocimiento al Companero Jack Sheinkman
- Tie tack (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Tie tacks - Charles B Rangel, P.D.N.Y. (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Tie tacks - GTB; second one depicts a stick figure fishing (Box 9, Folder 3)
- CLUW Pin (Box 9, Folder 4)
- ACTWU Pins - Texas District; Arkansas District; Southwest; PAC (Box 9, Folder 5)
- ACTWU pins (Box 9, Folder 6)
  4 pieces
- ACTWU, New York Joint Board Pin (shaped like shears); CATA, ACWIF pin (shaped like shears) (2) (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Flag shaped pins (5) - New York State AFL-CIO, ACTWU (Box 9, Folder 8)
- ACTWU pins (6) (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Mondale Ferraro pins from ACTWU (6) (Box 9, Folder 10)
- ILWU pin (fist holding a hook); United Garment Workers Union 100th Anniversary. Pin; 2 misc. pins (Box 9, Folder 11)
- America pins (2) (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Italian-American Labor Council pin; ACTWU pins (2); 2 misc. pins (Box 9, Folder 13)
- ACTWU pins (2); President of the United States of America Seal pin (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Union Yes pins (2); James Connolly, Irish-American Labor Coalition pin; Confederation de Trabajadorespin (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Images digitized from the collection. (Box 10)